Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series X. Re-election Campaign for Governor
1982
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.10
40 Linear Feet
The re-election campaign was officially kicked off in March 1982. Dick Thornburgh knew he still had goals to achieve, especially an economic development plan. Democrat three-term U.S. Congressman, Allen Ertel, of Williamsport, announced his candidacy for Governor in February 1982, and was joined by James Lloyd for Lieutenant Governor. Although the first statewide poll showed Thornburgh and Scranton with a 56-33 percent lead, Reagan's waning popularity in view of the economic recession was a danger sign for Republican candidates. After the election, the number of GOP Governors nationwide fell from twenty-three to sixteen and only three Republicans, in the largest states most affected by the recession, won. Of those Thornburgh's winning margin was by far the largest. The campaign files here document the Thornburgh administration's accomplishments to date, with related backup material and TV ads. The campaign news clippings monitor the progress of the campaign as do the MOR (Market Opinion Research) polls. The files are divided as follows: Campaign Plans and Announcement; Achievements Binders; Achievement Ads and Backup Information; Campaign Positions; Opposition Research, Potential Candidates; Opposition Research, Ertel and Lloyd; Campaign in Progress; Events; Press Files; News Clippings; and Post Election and Inaugural. There are four scrapbooks that contain some material not available elsewhere, particularly some staff notes and memoranda. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Organized crime -- United States; Economic development projects -- Pennsylvania; Industrial promotion -- Pennsylvania; Factory and trade waste -- Environmental aspects; Pollution -- Law and legislation; Education; Tourism -- Pennsylvania; Personal papers; Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania; Government; Public schools -- Pennsylvania; Politics; Business and Industry; School improvement programs -- Pennsylvania; Education -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Pennsylvania -- Economic conditions; Environment; Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson); Thornburgh, Dick; Pennsylvania. Governor -- Elections, 1982; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Lloyd, James R.; Ertel, Allen E.; Scranton, William W. (William Warren)
- Re-election Campaign for Governor, 1982; X.
  Scope and Contents note
  The Re-election Campaign began in earnest early in the fall of 1981. At that point three of the first years as Governor had passed and there were many agenda items, which had been checked off. "Neil Peirce, in a piece entitled 'Pennsylvania's Thornburgh: Extraordinary Governor,' stated [Thornburgh's] belief that 'political capital can be made of unadorned good management' and took note of 'the Thornburgh style - the calm, deliberate method he brought to Three Mile Island and now applies to virtually every problem ... If such a steady-as-you-go management is proving popular in Pennsylvania, why not elsewhere?'" (Evidence draft, p. 513). In spite of such praise and record of accomplishments, Thornburgh knew he still had goals to achieve, especially an all-important economic development plan, and knew at the outset there would be no landslide in the forthcoming election.
  Three-term U.S. Congressman, Allen Ertel, of Williamsport announced his candidacy for governor in February 1982, and was quickly endorsed by the Democratic State Committee, as was James Lloyd for Lieutenant Governor. Ertel's announcement speech "stated, falsely in both cases, that the state 'had the second highest unemployment rate in the nation' and that 'while the federal government has cut income taxes, the Thornburgh administration has raised them.' Such exaggerations and falsehoods were to characterize much of his campaign" (Evidence, p. 178). The nation was in recession at the time and Pennsylvania's unemployment rate reached as high as 11.3 percent in September 1982. "We consistently responded to Ertel's near-exclusive focus on the economy by noting the national character of our economic quandary, reminding voters that Pennsylvania was not 'an island of unemployment in a sea of prosperity'" (Evidence, p. 179).
  Thornburgh's re-election campaign was kicked off in March 1982, and at each stop accomplishments of the first term were emphasized. Included in the list were: "an end to corruption, an end to 'credit-card government,' a reduction in the bloated bureaucracy, a refusal to raise taxes and the revitalization of PennDOT ... In addition to continuing to work for better management, tax restraint and economic recovery, [Thornburgh] pledged to reform the welfare system, end the state's liquor monopoly and fight the burdensome and expensive twice-a-year auto inspections" (Evidence, p. 179). Television ads, available here online, primarily reviewed the record of Thornburgh's first term.
  Important endorsements were forthcoming and the first statewide poll, on October 1, conducted by the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, showed Thornburgh and Scranton with a 56-33 percent lead. However, Reagan's popularity was waning nationally in view of the economic recession and this was a danger sign for Republican candidates. "The Wall Street Journal weighed in with a piece describing [Thornburgh] as 'one of the political phenomena of this recession year' and having run 'a clean, efficient and economical state government.' The article included an interesting observation from Julius Uehlein, state AFL-CIO president: 'If it weren't for the economic issue, I imagine [Thornburgh] would be invincible'" (Evidence, p. 185). When all was said and done, virtually every major newspaper endorsed the Thornburgh-Scranton campaign across the state.
  Keeping in mind the Democrats' 678,000-voter registration advantage and a relentless attack by Ertel during this period of severe economic decline and increasing unemployment, there was reason for the Thornburgh camp to feel uneasy, despite its significant accomplishments. Perceptions of Thornburgh's achievements were seriously affected by national discontent and a Democratic tide swept the country that year. "Nationwide, the number of GOP governors tumbled from twenty-three to sixteen as Democrats defeated nine incumbents ... and only three Republicans [in the largest states most affected by the recession] won ... Of the three, [Thornburgh's] winning margin was by far the largest" (Evidence, p. 189).
  The campaign files here well document the message of accomplishment, with related backup material and TV ads proclaiming the facts. Also of note is the detailed opposition research, particularly about Allen Ertel. The campaign news clippings specifically monitor the progress of the campaign, it's ups and downs, odd incidents, endorsements, and ultimately the election results. The MOR (Market Opinion Research) polls are of particular interest as the campaign regularly tracked the race with its own polls. The files are divided as follows: Campaign Plans and Announcement; Achievements Binders; Achievement Ads and Backup Information; Campaign Positions; Opposition Research, Potential Candidates; Opposition Research (Ertel and Lloyd); Campaign in Progress; Events; Press Files; News Clippings; and Post Election and Inaugural.
  Of special interest to researchers will be the four scrapbooks assembled after the campaign, which track it in content as well as in the media. These were undertaken at the request of the candidate, immediately post election, and, in fact, contain some material not available elsewhere, particularly some staff notes and memoranda. These are colorful and informative and include issues, media coverage, internal campaign staff comments and notes, as well as campaign ephemera. These campaign scrapbooks have been reformatted for preservation purposes. All collection scrapbooks are enumerated in Section 21 here.
  - Campaign Plans and Announcement, 1.
    These files include various memos and reports by the Thornburgh staff, including Rick Stafford (RAS) and Jim Seif (JMS) and regarding the campaign. Included here is the Eddie Mahe report, an analysis by an outside consultant of re-election organization and strategy. Here also is the official announcement of Thornburgh's bid for reelection.
    - Rick Stafford (RAS) memos, November 9, 1981-July 20, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 1)
    - Jim Seif (JMS) memos, September 15, 1981-July 28, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 2)
    - Eddie Mahe's report on organizational aspects of Thornburgh-Scranton Campaign, June 3, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 3)
    - Voter registration proposal, May 12, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 4)
    - Announcement speech and news releases, February 28-March 3, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 5)
  - First Administration Achievements, 2.
    These files are collections of statements and facts assembled by the Thornburgh campaign, which document the achievements of the first term administration. Some of the topics included, for example, are: transportation, education, economic development, Three Mile Island, human services, farmers, women and minorities. For archival purposes, the files have been removed from their original binders and placed in folders. The term "binders," however, has been preserved in the titles, indicative of the original order. "Bullets" in effect describes a crisp, clean statement of an accomplishment, and has been retained here as used by the campaign.
    - Achievements binders, 1978-1982 (Box 124, Folder 6-8)
    - First Update to achievements binders, April 9, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 9-10)
    - Bullets, May 3-July 28, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 11-13)
  - Achievement Ads and Backup Documentation, 3.
    These files contain specific "backup" information regarding campaign issues and controversies, as well as the campaign platform and ads scripts. Issues have a further breakdown here relevant to constituencies (for example: women, or blacks), and geography (Philadelphia or Northwest, Pennsylvania, for example). The seven specific sections of these files are as follows: Achievement Ads and Media; Campaign Platform; Major Issues; Constituencies; Geographic Issue Background; Reports, News Releases, and Clippings; and Campaign Controversies. Materials in these files include, for example: memos, news clippings and reports.
    - Achievement Ads and Media
      - General election media, scripts for television spots and advertisements, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 14)
      - Television scripts, 1982 (Box 124, Folder 15)
      - Ads, scripts, drafts and staff memos regarding print media and direct mailings, 1982 (Box 125, Folder 1)
      - Ads/Scripts backup references, August-September, 1982 (Box 125, Folder 2)
      - Bailey Deardourff consultants, media and advertising, 1982 (Box 125, Folder 3)
      - Press kits, 1982 (Box 125, Folder 4)
    - Campaign Platform
      - 1982 Platform, September, 1981-1982 (Box 125, Folder 5)
    - Major Issues
      - Integrity in Government, 1979-1982 (Box 125, Folder 6)
      - Budget and taxes, 1980-1982 (Box 125, Folder 7-8)
      - Size and efficiency in government, January, 1981-October, 1982 (Box 125, Folder 9-10)
      - Economic development, March, 1980-May, 1982 (Box 125, Folder 11-13)
      - Economic development: memos, June, 1982-October, 1982 (Box 126, Folder 1-3)
      - Transportation: memos, clippings, and correspondence, October, 1981-October, 1982 (Box 126, Folder 4)
      - Transportation: PennDOT news releases, Districts 1-4, 1979-1982 (Box 126, Folder 5)
      - Transportation: PennDOT news releases, Districts 5-43, 1979-1982 (Box 126, Folder 6)
      - Education: clippings and memos, January, 1979-November, 1981 (Box 126, Folder 7)
      - Crime, June, 1979-December, 1982 (Box 126, Folder 8)
      - Crime, June, 1979-December, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 1-2)
      - Human services: memos, clippings, and news releases, December, 1981-October, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 3)
      - Human services: health, February, 1979-November, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 4)
      - Human services: welfare, June, 1979-December, 1981 (Box 127, Folder 5)
      - Human services: welfare memos, clippings, news releases and correspondence, March 9, 1982-August 2, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 6)
      - Human services: senior citizens and aging, December, 1979-September, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 7)
      - Human services: handicapped, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 8)
      - Energy and environment: memos and clippings, November, 1979-August, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 9)
      - Three Mile Island (TMI): backup references, correspondence, memos, and clippings, April, 1979-July, 1981 (Box 127, Folder 10-11)
      - Three Mile Island (TMI): clippings, April, 1979-May 25, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 12)
      - Liquor Control Board (LCB), July, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 13)
    - Constituencies
      - Blacks, November, 1977-January, 1982 (Box 127, Folder 14-15)
      - Blacks: correspondence, news releases, and clippings, February-October, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 1)
      - Ethnics and other minorities, November, 1979-October, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 2-3)
      - Women, July, 1979-July, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 4)
      - Senior citizens, July, 1980-October, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 5)
      - Farmers, January, 1979-December, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 6-7)
      - Veterans, May, 1979-September, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 8)
      - Sportsmen, March, 1980-July, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 9)
      - Labor, January, 1981-August, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 10)
      - Arts in Pennsylvania, April-June, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 11)
      - Consumers, March-September, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 12)
      - Firefighters, September, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 13)
      - Local Government, June, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 14)
    - Geographic Issue Background
      - Allegheny County, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 15)
      - Philadelphia County, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 16)
      - Northeast, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 17)
      - Northwest, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 18)
      - Harrisburg area, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 19)
      - Rest of Southeast, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 20)
      - Allentown, Bethlehem, Easton, 1982 (Box 128, Folder 21)
    - Reports, News Releases, and Clippings
      - Policy reports, 1980-1981 (Box 128, Folder 22-23)
      - Major news releases and speeches, March 7, 1979-November 18, 1981 (Box 129, Folder 1-2)
      - Abortion: news releases and clippings, 1980-1982 (Box 129, Folder 3)
      - Thornburgh general files: favorable clippings, January, 1980-May, 1981 (Box 129, Folder 4)
    - Campaign Controversies
      - Scanlon gag order: memos, clippings, correspondence, September, 1981-May, 1982 (Box 129, Folder 5)
      - Women, Infants, Children (WIC): Legislative, Budget and Finance Committee report, January 22, 1982 (Box 129, Folder 6)
      - Women, Infants, Children (WIC): memos, correspondence, remarks by Secretary Muller, transcripts of remarks to Legislature by Representative Itkin, and clippings, April, 1980-September, 1981 (Box 129, Folder 7)
      - Salaries: memos, news releases and clippings, February, 1979-November, 1980 (Box 129, Folder 8)
      - Gay Pride: proclamation, pro and con clippings, June, 1982 (Box 129, Folder 9)
      - Bond counsel: reports, memos and clippings, 1981-1982 (Box 129, Folder 10)
      - PSEA: Truth Squad press kits (Ertel and Thornburgh/Scranton) and backup memos, 1981-1982 (Box 129, Folder 11)
      - PSEA: clippings, news releases, 1981-October, 1982 (Box 129, Folder 12-13)
      - Wives and girlfriends, May, 1979 (Box 129, Folder 14)
      - Robert Ging (former DER staff attorney) controversy: news releases and clippings, January, 1982 (Box 129, Folder 15)
      - Foreign travel: news releases and clippings, 1980 (Box 130, Folder 1)
      - Thornburgh/Scranton feud: clippings, 1981 (Box 130, Folder 2)
      - Graterford: news releases, clippings, and Paul Critchlow memo, November, 1981-February, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 3)
      - Public relations empire: memos, correspondence, and clippings, July, 1978-August, 1981 (Box 130, Folder 4)
      - Travel: US News and World Report article, March 15, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 5)
  - Campaign Positions, 4.
    These files represent specific campaign positions and issues related to various constituencies and differing geographic areas. Some of the topics included, for example are: transportation, integrity in government, education, economic development, crime, women, fire fighters, minorities and farmers. They are grouped as follows: General Issues, Constituencies, and Geographic Areas.
    - Issues
      - Integrity in Government, April 14, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 6)
      - General positions, 1980-1982 (Box 130, Folder 7)
      - Budget and taxes, March-September, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 8)
      - Size and efficiency in government, articles, September 12, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 9)
      - Economic development, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 10)
      - Transportation, March-May, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 11)
      - Education, February-September, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 12)
      - Crime, March-September, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 13)
      - Human services, protest and March flier, March 23, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 14)
      - Human services, health, March 19, 1982-April 6, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 15)
      - Human services, welfare, March 19, 1982-April 9, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 16)
      - Energy, February 1, 1982-March 23, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 17)
      - Environment, February 22, 1982-April 21, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 18)
      - Liquor Control Board (LCB), January, 1981-March 9, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 19)
    - Constituencies
      - Blacks, March-September, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 20)
      - Ethnics and other minorities, September, 1981-June, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 21)
      - Women, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 22)
      - Senior Citizens, March, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 23)
      - Farmers, 1979-1982 (Box 130, Folder 24)
      - Veterans, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 25)
      - Sportsmen, September, 1981-October, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 26)
      - Labor, February, 1982-October, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 27-28)
      - Business, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 29)
      - Profile of PA's 17th District Congressional candidates, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 30)
      - Democrats, February-July, 1982 (Box 130, Folder 31)
      - Firefighters, April-September, 1982 (Box 131, Folder 1)
      - Local government, April-June, 1982 (Box 131, Folder 2)
      - Small business, April-September, 1982 (Box 131, Folder 3)
      - Law enforcement groups, 1982 (Box 131, Folder 4)
      - Consumer, 1982 (Box 131, Folder 5)
      - Federal, February-April, 1982 (Box 131, Folder 6)
      - People file, February-March, 1982 (Box 131, Folder 7)
  - Opposition Research, Potential Candidates, 5.
    These files contain research on potential candidates. State Auditor General Al Benedict early was perceived as a likely candidate for governor and thus there is more opposition research regarding his record. Other potential candidates include: James Manderino, Steve Douglas, Pete Flaherty, Bill Green, and others. These files primarily consist of correspondence and news clippings.
    - Al Benedict
      - Auditor General's office: administration (budgets, etc.), 1980 (Box 131, Folder 8)
      - Auditor General's office: general information, 1976-1981 (Box 131, Folder 9)
      - Biography, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 10)
      - Blacks and minorities, 1979-1981 (Box 131, Folder 11)
      - Campaign ads, 1982 (Box 131, Folder 12)
      - Complaints and tips: lack of responsiveness by Auditor General Office, 1979-1980 (Box 131, Folder 13)
      - Democratic Party relations, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 14)
      - Senator Duffield, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 15)
      - Liquor Control Board (LCB) audits: report regarding Thornburgh and Benedict, 1976-1980 (Box 131, Folder 16)
      - Negative material regarding Benedict, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 17)
      - PSEA, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 18)
      - Relations with the press, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 19)
      - Lenora Smith (Auditor General chief counsel), 1978-1980 (Box 131, Folder 20)
      - State Hospital closings, May, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 21)
      - Veterans groups, June 25, 1981 (Box 131, Folder 22)
      - Welfare fraud, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 23)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, notes, summaries, 1977-1981 (Box 131, Folder 24)
      - Correspondence with Governor Thornburgh, 1979-1981 (Box 131, Folder 25)
      - Benedict correspondence with Thornburgh administration, 1979-1981 (Box 131, Folder 26)
      - Personnel reports, 1979 (Box 131, Folder 27)
      - List of employees, list of Democratic Party contributors, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 28)
      - Employees/Party contributor clippings, 1977-1982 (Box 131, Folder 29)
      - Campaign expense report, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 30)
      - Benedict vs. Kury race, 1980 (Box 131, Folder 31)
      - Benedict vs. Kury radio debate, January-May, 1980 (Box 132, Folder 1)
      - Clippings, 1979-1982 (Box 132, Folder 2-5)
    - Other Potential Candidates
      - Richard Caliguiri, 1979-1981 (Box 132, Folder 6)
      - Robert P. Casey, former Auditor General, 1972-1982 (Box 132, Folder 7)
      - Joseph Chilzer (1982 Gubernatorial candidate) (Box 132, Folder 8)
      - Steve Douglas (1982 Gubernatorial candidate) (Box 132, Folder 9)
      - Bob Edgar, 1979-1981 (Box 132, Folder 10)
      - Pete Flaherty, 1978-1980 (Box 132, Folder 11)
      - Dick Fuerle (1982 Libertarian candidate) (Box 132, Folder 12)
      - Bill Green, 1980-1981 (Box 132, Folder 13)
      - Alvin J. Jacobson, 1982 (Box 132, Folder 14)
      - Craig Lewis, 1981 (Box 132, Folder 15)
      - James Manderino, 1981 (Box 132, Folder 16)
      - Michael O'Pake, 1980-1981 (Box 132, Folder 17)
      - Ed Rendell, 1980-1981 (Box 132, Folder 18)
      - Milton J. Shapp, 1978-1981 (Box 132, Folder 19)
      - Cyril Wecht, 1980-1981 (Box 132, Folder 20)
      - Edward Zemprelli, 1979-1981 (Box 132, Folder 21)
      - Mark Zola (Socialist Workers' Party), 1982 (Box 132, Folder 22)
      - Articles on miscellaneous candidates: Philadelphia Magazine "Guide to the 1981 Political Machine" and Philadelphia Inquirer "Pennsylvania Legislators Junkets", April, 1981-February, 1982 (Box 132, Folder 23)
  - Opposition Research, Ertel and Lloyd, 6.
    These files contain extensive research on the two actual candidates for the 1982 election: Allen Ertel (Governor) and James Lloyd (Lieutenant Governor). They contain research on many of the same areas of the Thornburgh "achievements": economic development, budget and taxes, energy and environment, women, farmers, and others. The Ertel files are divided into six sections: Research binders, General issues, Constituencies, Miscellaneous issues, Personal and political history, and 1982 Campaign. The James Lloyd files include research on key issues, such as welfare reform, education, campaign expenses, and Senate voting record. They are divided into three sections: General issues, Personal and political history, and 1982 Campaign.
    - Allen Ertel (D), Governor
      - Research Binders
        - Research binder, Volume 1: Personal and campaign conduct, Government and economic issues and constituencies, 1982 (Box 132, Folder 24)
        - Research binder, Volume 2: Human Service issues and constituencies, Miscellaneous, Lloyd, Appendices, 1982 (Box 133, Folder 1-2)
        - Research binder annotated by Thornburgh, Volume 1: Personal and campaign conduct, Government and economic issues and constituencies, 1982 (Box 133, Folder 3-4)